Shenglai Zeng

https://slz-ai.github.io/

☑ shenglaizeng@gmail.com

□ (+1)517-9747616

RESEARCH INTEREST

I am a first-year PhD student at Michigan State University advised by Professor Jiliang Tang. My current research interests are mainly about Trustworthy AI, especially safety-related topics about large language models(LLMs) and retrieval augmented generation(RAG). I also worked on federated learning for years.

EDUCATION

Michigan State University

East Lansing, U.S

DSE Lab/PhD students in Computer Science and Engineering

Sept 2023-Present

Advisor: Jiliang Tang

Lab: Data Science and Engineering Lab Research Direction: Trustworthy AI

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China

Yingcai Honor School/B.Sc in Computer Science and Engineering

Chengdu, China

Sept 2019-Present

CGPA: 3.98/4.00

Weighted Average: 93.97/100(1st among 100 students) Honors: The Most Outstanding Students Award of UESTC

PREPRINTS

• **Shenglai Zeng***, Jiankun Zhang*, Pengfei He, Yue Xing, Yiding Liu, Han Xu, Jie Ren, Shuaiqiang Wang, Dawei Yin, Yi Chang, Jiliang Tang

The Good and The Bad: Exploring Privacy Issues in Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) Submitted to ACL-2024

• **Shenglai Zeng***, Yaxin Li*, Jie Ren, Yiding Liu, Han Xu, Pengfei He, Yue Xing, Shuaiqiang Wang, Jiliang Tang, Dawei Yin

Exploring Memorization in Fine-tuned Language Models

Submitted to ACL-2024

 Jie Ren, Han Xu, Pengfei He, Yingqian Cui, Shenglai Zeng, Jiankun Zhang, Hongzhi Wen, Jiayuan Ding, Hui Liu, Yi Chang, Jiliang Tang

Copyright Protection in Generative AI: A Technical Perspective

Pre-print

- Han Xu, Jie Ren, Pengfei He, Yingqian Cui, Shenglai Zeng, Hui Liu, Jiliang Tang, Amy Liu
 On the Generalization of Training-based ChatGPT Detection Methods Submitted to ACL-2024
- Pengfei He, Han Xu, Yue Xing, Jie Ren, Yingqian Cui, Shenglai Zeng, Jiliang Tang, Makoto Yamada, Mohammad Sabokrou

Confidence-driven Sampling for Backdoor Attacks

Submitted to ICML-2024

PUBLICATIONS

 Pengfei He, Han Xu, Jie Ren, Yingqian Cui, Shenglai Zeng, Hui Liu, Charu Aggarwal, Jiliang Tang Sharpness-aware Data Poisoning Attack

ICLR-2024 Spotlight

- Juanhui Li, Harry Shomer, Haitao Mao, Shenglai Zeng, Yao Ma, Neil Shah, Jiliang Tang, Dawei Yin Evaluating graph neural networks for link prediction: Current pitfalls and new benchmarking NIPS-2023 Benchmark
- **Shenglai Zeng**, Zonghang Li, Hongfang Yu, Zhihao Zhang, Long Luo, Bo Li, Dusit Niyato HFedMS: Heterogeneous Federated Learning with Memorable Data Semantics in Industrial Metaverse.

IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing

- Shenglai Zeng, Zonghang Li, Hongfang Yu, Yihong He, Zenglin Xu, Dusit Niyato, Han Yu
 Heterogeneous Federated Learning via Grouped Sequential-to-Parallel Training
 International Conference on Database Systems for Advanced Applications (DASFAA-2022)
- Jiaqi Wang*, Shenglai Zeng*, Zewei Long, Yaqing Wang, Houping Xiao, Fenglong Ma Knowledge-Enhanced Semi-Supervised Federated Learning for Aggregating Heterogeneous Lightweight Clients in IoT SDM-2023

Patent

Shenglai Zeng, Zonghang Li, Yihong He, Xun Zhang, Hongfang Yu, Gang Sun
"A Hierarchical User Training Management Architecture and Training Strategy for Non-i.i.d Data" Chinese
patent

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

DSE Lab, Michigan State University

Lansing, U.S

Research Assistant/Research on Trustworthy AI and LLM-safety

Sept 2023 - Present

- -Advisor: Professor Jiliang Tang
- Identify and mitigate the real privacy issues of LLMs.
- Diverse attack/defense techniques on LLM systems.
- Deeper understanding of underlying mechnism behind LLMs, especially knowledge extraction perspective.
- Leaverage LLMs to enhance/empower challanging applications and tasks.

Search Science Team, Baidu.Inc

Beijing, China

Research Intern/Research on the memorization of LLM

May 2023 - Present

- -Mentor: Dr. Yiding Liu and Dr. Dawei Yin
- Investigating the memorization behavior and privacy implications of fine-tuned LLMs.
 One conference Paper submitted to ICLR 2023(First author)
- Currently worked on privacy risks of Retrieval LMs and AI-agents.

Intelligent Networking and Applications Research Center, UESTC

Chengdu, China

Research Assistant/Research on the Optimization of Federated Learning

Sept 2020 - Jun 2023

- -Mentor: Professor Hongfang Yu and Dr. Zonghang Li
- Proposed a novel idea of Sequential-to-Parallel training in FL.
 One conference Paper accepted by DASFAA 2022(First author)
- Investigated the application of FL in Industrial Metaverse. One journal paper accepted by IEEE TCC(First author).

The Pennsylvania State University

Pennsylvania, USA

Online Intern/Research on Semi-supervised Federated Learning

Jun 2021 - Jun 2022

-Mentor: Professor Fenglong Ma

- Implemented a semi-supervised federated learning system combined with novel personalized punning and structure-aware collaborative distillation techniques.
 Paper accepted by to SDM 2022(Co-First Author)
- Currently focusing on FL with different model structures.

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, Canada

Summer Intern/Federated Data Evaluation with Unlearning

Jun 2022 - Sept 2022

- -Mentor: Professor Xiaoxiao Li
- Try to use the concept of cooperative game to evaluate the importance of data of participating users in federated learning.
- Try to accelerate the evaluation process and straggler problem using federated unlearning.

The University of Chicago

Chicago, USA

Online Intern/Research on the IOT & Sensing Security

Mar 2020 - Mar 2021

- -Mentor: Shinan Liu(PhD candidate)
- Tried to use audio data collected by microphone to reconstruct user's state of motion during recording time.
- Proposed a mathematical-physical model to explain the correlation between different sensors' responses to motion.

KEY SKILLS

Programming Language Python, C, C++, Java, Matlab

Research Tool Latex, Overleaf

AI Framework Pytorch, Mxnet, Tensorflow

Network Cisco Certified Network Associate(CCNA)

SELECTED ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Exploring Memorization in Fine-tuned Language Models

May 2023- Oct 2023

- Extensively studied the memorization effect of LLMs during the fine-tuning stage across different tasks.
- Fine-tuning Risks: Utilizing copyrighted or private data in fine-tuning poses privacy/IP risks.
- Task Disparity: Summarization & Dialogue show high memorization, while QA and Classification are lower.
- Attention's Role: High memorization tasks have uniform, sparse attention patterns. We unravel the nuances between attention & memorization.
- Solution in Sight: Multi-task fine-tuning buffers against high memorization vs single-task techniques.

Federated Learning Framework Design in Industrial Metaverse

Feb 2022 - Present

- **Background**: This work mainly focuses on the non-i.i.d streaming data collected by distributed edge devices in Industrial Metaverse.(e.g. OCR applications in industrial parks.)
- Challenge: data heterogeneity/limited band width/ catastrophic forgetting towards streaming data
- A dynamic FL training paradigm designed for rapidly changing streaming data while eliminating data heterogeneity.
- A knowledge maintained online learning method for FL to prevent catastrophic forgetting
- Task decomposition in federated learning to reduce communication pressure on edge networks
- This work is accepted by IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing.

Semi-Supervised Federated Learning for IoT

Jun 2021 - Sept 2022

- This work aims to develop an applicable federated learning mechanism for IoT devices in semi-supervised settings, considering personalization and communication efficiency simultaneously.
- We introduced neural network pruning techniques into semi-supervised federated learning and a novel structure-aware collaborative distillation approach which can aggregate models with different structures.
- This work is accepted by SDM 2023.

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- The Most Outstanding Students Award of UESTC (Highest honor in UESTC, Only10 students are awarded)
- **National Scholarship** in the session of 2019-2020. (Highest honor of undergraduate student)
- WAC Scholarship in the session of 2020-2021.(Only 10 undergraduate students in UESTC are awarded each year)
- 1st Outstanding Academic Scholarship in 2020,2021,and 2022.(Top 5 % students)

Services

• **Program Committee or Reviewer:** IEEE TKDE, IoT-J, IEEE Trans on Information Forensics Security, MICCAI Workshop on Distributed, Collaborative and Federated Learning (DeCaF-2022)